Guide to the Feminist Women's Health Center Records, 1973-2003 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Feminist Women's Health Center records 1973-2003 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Feminist Women's Health Center.
76.8 linear feet Extent: 51,350 Items
The Feminist Women's Health Center in Atlanta, Georgia, was founded in 1976 by a group of women dissatisfied with the health care options and information available to them and who desired to change this situation. The clinic started in 1977 with self-help groups where women were able to learn from each other and themselves through open discussions. It expanded to offer a full range of clinical services (including providing access to birth control and contraception, abortion, donor insemination, and pregnancy care) as well as educational, outreach, and advocacy programs, addressing subjects such as sexual hygiene, sex, and sexually transmitted diseases. Collection is comprised of files documenting the development and daily operations of the Feminist Women's Health Center, a feminist non-profit women's healthcare center, from the years 1973-2003. Major components of the collection include files from research studies conducted at the center, policies and procedures for maintaining the center, and incidents of anti-abortion protests at the center, specifically involving the group Operation Rescue. The National Abortion Federation, the professional association of abortion providers in the United States and Canada, also figures prominently throughout these records. The collection is organized into six series: Administrative Files, Clinic Files, Subject Files, Financial Material, Legal Files, and Audiovisual Material. The collection also contains a physically separate Closed Series, comprised of materials from the prior six series that are currently closed to research.
RL.00427
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
RESTRICTION: The majority of the collection is open for research. However, at the request of the donor (Feminist Women's Health Center), materials deemed sensitive in nature have been physically segregated and closed to research. These materials have been relocated to the Closed Series and are housed in boxes 104-125. In addition, some sensitive materials remain open to research but have been redacted. Originals of redacted material are not available for research and have been returned to the donor.
Use of audiovisual materials will require use copies to be made. Patrons should contact Research Services staff in advance if use of these materials is desired.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Feminist Women's Health Center Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in November 2003.
Historical Note
The Feminist Women's Health Center in Atlanta, Georgia, was founded in 1976 by a group of women dissatisfied with the health care options and information available to them and who desired to change this situation. The clinic started in 1977 with self-help groups where women were able to learn from each other and themselves through open discussions. It expanded to offer a full range of clinical services (including providing access to birth control and contraception, abortion, donor insemination, and pregnancy care) as well as educational, outreach, and advocacy programs, addressing subjects such as sexual hygiene, sex, and sexually transmitted diseases.
Collection Overview
Collection is comprised of files documenting the development and daily operations of the Feminist Women's Health Center (FWHC), a feminist non-profit women's healthcare center, from the years 1974-2003. Major components of the collection include files from research studies conducted at the center, policies and procedures for maintaining the center, and incidents of anti-abortion protests at the center, specifically involving the group Operation Rescue. The National Abortion Federation, the professional association of abortion providers in the United States and Canada, also figures prominently throughout these records. The collection is organized into six series: Administrative Files, Clinic Files, Subject Files, Financial Material, Legal Files, and Audiovisual Material. The collection also contains a physically segregated Closed Series.
The Administrative Files Series most clearly documents the day-to-day operations of the FWHC. Materials in this series include policies, procedures, and guidelines for operation of the center; minutes and notes from a range of meetings held by the center; personnel files; and schedules. This series contains four subseries: General Administrative Files, Meetings, Personnel Files, and Schedules.
Materials in the Clinic Files Series include a range of records related to clinical services provided and research studies conducted at the FWHC. This series has been divided into four subseries: Statistics, Laboratory Statistics, Research, and Patient Education Information.
The Subject Files Series includes files maintained by the staff of the FWHC on a range of topics related to women's health issues, events, local information, and other women's health clinics. This series contains two subseries: a General subseries which covers these subjects broadly, and an Anti-Abortion Violence subseries which focuses specifically on anti-abortion protests at the FWHC and other locations, the anti-abortion movement in the United States, and pro-choice efforts to counter this movement.
Items in the Financial Material Series consist of records, reports, and files documenting the financial situation of the FWHC between the years 1982 and 2001. These files detail the intricacies involved in operating a women's health clinic from a financial standpoint.
The Legal Files Series contains files related to legal issues faced by the FWHC, including lawsuits and legislation which would affect women's reproductive health and the clinic.
The Audiovisual Material Series consists of 28 audiocassettes and 11 videocassettes. Audiocassettes are primarily recordings of workshops, conference sessions, and events. Videocassettes are primarily educational. One videocassette documents anti-abortion protesters outside the FWHC.
The Closed Series consists of sensitive materials removed from the previous six series and CLOSED to research.
Collection Arrangement
Collection is arranged into six series: Administrative Files, Clinic Files, Subject Files, Financial Material, Legal Files, and Audiovisual Material.
Sensitive material from each of these series has been physically segregated into the Closed Series, comprising boxes 104-125.
Subject Headings
Abortion -- Georgia; Abortion -- United States; Abortion services -- Employees; Abortion services -- Georgia; Abortion services -- United States; Atlanta (Ga.) -- History -- 20th century; Atlanta (Ga.) -- History -- 21st century; Audiocassettes; Birth control -- United States; Contraception -- United States; Family life education; Feminism -- Georgia; Feminism -- United States; Feminist Women's Health Center; Health education; Hygiene, Sexual; National Abortion Federation (U.S.); Nonprofit organizations -- Georgia; Operation Rescue (Organization); Political violence -- United States; Pregnancy; Pro-choice movement -- Georgia; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Pro-life movement -- Georgia; Pro-life movement -- United States; Sex; Sexually transmitted diseases; Vertical files; Videocassettes; Women -- Health and hygiene -- Georgia; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States; Women -- Health and hygiene -- Research -- United States; Women's health services -- Law and legislation -- United States; Women's health services -- Georgia; Women's health services -- United States; Women's rights -- Georgia; Women's rights -- United States; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Files Series, 1974-2002 and undated, (20 boxes)
  The Administrative Files most clearly document the day-to-day operations of the Feminist Women's Health Center (FWHC). Materials in this series include policies, procedures, and guidelines for operation of the center; minutes and notes from a range of meetings held by the center; personnel files, including training manuals and job descriptions; and schedules.
  This series contains four subseries: General Administrative Files, Meetings, Personnel Files, and Schedules.
  RESTRICTION: Sensitive materials in this series have been redacted or relocated to the Closed Series.
  - General Administrative Files, 1974-2002, (16 boxes)
    Consists primarily of files documenting policies, procedures, and guidelines for the operation of the FWHC. Original folder titles were retained whenever possible. Within the subseries are alphabetical runs of files and this order has been retained. Other related files appear in clusters as well, and users are encouraged to use the keyword find feature of their Internet browsers (accessible by clicking Ctrl-F) to locate additional similar files within the document.
    - Program assessment (Box 1)
    - National Practitioner Data Bank Guidebook, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Clinical staff (Box 1)
    - Nonprofit marketing, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Parental notification forms (Box 1)
    - Abortion training (Box 1)
    - Feminist Women's Health Center (FWHC) therapeutic sonogram approach (Box 1)
    - FWHC offered services (Box 1)
    - Women of the world (Box 1)
    - Log forms, blank, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Policies and procedures for ambulatory surgical centers (Box 1)
    - FWHC policies, procedures, and guidelines (Box 2)
    - Clinical policies, procedures, and guidelines (Box 2)
    - Forms (Box 2)
    - Instructions (Box 2)
    - Training/Lab (Box 2)
    - Consents (Box 2)
    - Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) packet (Box 2)
    - Depo Provera injection log (Box 2)
    - Driver responsibility (Box 2)
    - Digoxin injection form (Box 2)
    - Complication calls grid (Box 2)
    - Cytotec notes (Box 2)
    - Coordinator's day sheet, sample (Box 2)
    - Chart marker (Box 2)
    - Clinic summary, sample (Box 2)
    - Colposcopy/biopsy form (Box 2)
    - Colposcopy set up (Box 2)
    - Autoclave (Box 2)
    - Parental notification (Box 2)
    - Old forms (Box 2)
    - Training materials (Box 2)
    - Rape crisis centers (Box 2)
    - Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) program (Box 2)
    - Lesbian health and outreach (Box 2)
    - Multilingual health education resource guide (Box 2)
    - Customer service information (Box 2)
    - Applications, sample (Box 2)
    - Daily assignment sheets, sample (Box 2)
    - Nursing assignment sheets, sample (Box 2)
    - Absence report (Box 2)
    - Anesthesia standards (Box 2)
    - Acclaim laboratories (Box 2)
    - Abortion injunction (Box 2)
    - Americans with Disabilities Act (Box 2)
    - ADP Injunction (Box 2)
    - Atlanta health care providers (Box 2)
    - BFI waste (Box 2)
    - Business license- Atlanta (Box 2)
    - Bomb threat drills (Box 2)
    - Medical bylaws (Box 3)
    - Cobb County (Box 3)
    - COBRA (Box 3)
    - CRAE report forms (Box 3)
    - Complication calls training (Box 3)
    - MedGyn call tags (Box 3)
    - Cellular phone contract (Box 3)
    - Certified Medical Assistant information (Box 3)
    - Charting errors policy (Box 3)
    - Community outreach forms (Box 3)
    - CompuMed Pharmaceuticals (Box 3)
    - Crawford Long Hospital consents (Box 3)
    - DeKalb medical consent form (Box 3)
    - Defibrillator log sheets (Box 3)
    - Dinamap information (Box 3)
    - Emergency flow sheet (Box 3)
    - Emergency checklist (Box 3)
    - Exit interview (Box 3)
    - Exposure determination form (Box 3)
    - Fax cover (Box 3)
    - Fire marshal (Box 3)
    - Forensic ID testing (Box 3)
    - Frontier School of Midwifery and Family Nursing (Box 3)
    - Georgia Medical Gases, Inc. (Box 3)
    - FWHC inventory (Box 3)
    - Georgia Abortion Rights Action League (GARAL) (Box 3)
    - Grant proposals (Box 3)
    - Georgia nursing law (Box 3)
    - Georgia State University nursing student contracts (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for hand washing and hospital environmental control, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Health worker training form (Box 3)
    - Incident reports, sample (Box 3)
    - Interviewing (Box 3)
    - Investigation and evaluation form (Box 3)
    - IV certification forms (Box 3)
    - KODE team system (Box 3)
    - Lab (Box 3)
    - Lab technician training form (Box 3)
    - Laminaria training (Box 3)
    - Latin American Association (Box 3)
    - MA schools (Box 3)
    - Georgia Medicaid (Box 3)
    - Managing personnel (Box 3)
    - Malpractice insurance forms, blank (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Medicaid information (Box 3)
    - Monthly pathology logs, blank (Box 3)
    - Microscope (Box 3)
    - Mifepristone and Misoprostol (M&M), 1995 (Box 3)
    - National Abortion Federation (NAF) visit, 1999 (Box 3)
    - NAF (Box 3)
    - New employee orientation checklist (Box 3)
    - Nursing agency time receipts (Box 3)
    - National Organization for Women (NOW) vs. Scheidler (Box 3)
    - Nurse orientation (Box 3)
    - Orientation checklist (Box 3)
    - PTO Forms (Box 3)
    - Partial birth abortion (Box 3)
    - Pharmacy regulations (Box 3)
    - Personnel file checklist (Box 3)
    - Payment request forms, blank (Box 3)
    - Payroll advance request (Box 3)
    - Pelvic exam and laminaria insertion (Box 3)
    - Pelvic modeling (Box 3)
    - Current phlebotomy training and certification forms (Box 3)
    - Protective measures forms (Box 3)
    - Reference check forms (Box 3)
    - Research proposal guidelines (Box 3)
    - Nurse training forms (Box 3)
    - Staff schedule (Box 3)
    - Sisterlove, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Separation notice (Box 3)
    - Sonogram protocol (Box 3)
    - Sonogram technician contract (Box 3)
    - Sonogram technician training forms (Box 4)
    - Substance abuse policy (Box 4)
    - Supply request forms (Box 4)
    - Strategic planning (Box 4)
    - Spanish class proposal (Box 4)
    - Training information (Box 4)
    - Time card corrections (Box 4)
    - Training reports evaluations (Box 4)
    - Termination reports (Box 4)
    - Annual Tuberculosis (TB) forms (Box 4)
    - User guides (pager, etc.) (Box 4)
    - Uterine sign charts (Box 4)
    - New health worker readings (Box 4)
    - BCP screening training (Box 4)
    - Birth control methods training (Box 4)
    - Sample charts, (7 folders) (Box 4)
    - Past training tests (Box 4)
    - Annual exam form (Box 4)
    - Amendment to authorization (Box 4)
    - Autoclave cleaning log (Box 4)
    - After care check-up (Box 4)
    - Against medical advice to leave (Box 4)
    - Homework daily assignment (Box 4)
    - Break/lunch schedule (Box 4)
    - Drivers' information (Box 4)
    - Drug record/control log (Box 4)
    - Employee health form/assessment (Box 4)
    - Expiration supply check list (Box 4)
    - Emergency cart checklist (Box 4)
    - Emergency checklist (Box 4)
    - Emergency exit (Box 4)
    - "FACE" (Box 4)
    - Complications follow up log, blank (Box 4)
    - Coordinator's follow up log, blank (Box 4)
    - Gynecological sonogram worksheet (Box 4)
    - Health history (Box 4)
    - Hotel log, blank (Box 4)
    - Hotel referral logs (Box 4)
    - Information call log (Box 4)
    - Inter-office request form (Box 4)
    - Instrument cleaning logs (Box 4)
    - Laboratory reports (Box 4)
    - Daily lab log (Box 4)
    - Lab request form (Box 4)
    - Laboratory logs (Box 4)
    - PRS lab report (Box 4)
    - Lab temperature checklist (Box 4)
    - Medicaid lab sheets (Box 4)
    - Medication orders (Box 4)
    - Medical record requests (Box 4)
    - Marriage license (Box 4)
    - M&M drug count/control log (Box 4)
    - Mirena consent (Box 4)
    - NAF daily abortion log (Box 4)
    - New employee orientation checklist (Box 4)
    - Notes (Box 4)
    - Nursing staff orientation training (Box 4)
    - Oral contraceptive log (Box 4)
    - Pap letters (Box 4)
    - Physician exam form (Box 4)
    - Pre-procedure notes (Box 4)
    - Physician's lab requisition (Box 4)
    - Physician's notes (Box 4)
    - Prescription record (Box 4)
    - Pregnancy-related services appointment checklist (Box 4)
    - Physician's certification for marriage license in Georgia (Box 4)
    - Procedure for disinfecting plastic aspirator tubing (Box 4)
    - Procedure for disinfection (Box 4)
    - Pap letter: Koilocytotic Atypia (Box 4)
    - Pap letter: Atypia (Box 4)
    - Personnel review (Box 4)
    - Post-clinic instrument check (Box 4)
    - Pregnancy screening form (Box 4)
    - Pathology log (Box 4)
    - Reception log (Box 4)
    - Refund request (Box 4)
    - Refusal of medication (Box 4)
    - Refusal of beta subunit pregnancy test (Box 4)
    - Revisit form (Box 4)
    - Self-help notes (Box 4)
    - Self-help clinic (Box 4)
    - School/work excuse (Box 4)
    - Shortened abortion group (Box 4)
    - Shortened dilation and evacuation (D and E) group (Box 4)
    - Sonogram results (Box 4)
    - State of Georgia (Box 4)
    - Itemized statement of services (Box 4)
    - Staff reimbursement forms (Box 4)
    - Statement of understanding (Box 4)
    - Daily clinic summary (Box 4)
    - Ultrasound (Box 4)
    - Ultrasound technician (Box 4)
    - Urine culture- in house (Box 4)
    - Work excuse (Box 4)
    - Weekly drug count (Box 4)
    - Weekly/monthly AB statistics sheets (Box 4)
    - Well Woman set up list (Box 4)
    - Genesis Shelter reproductive health training model (Box 5)
    - The Women's Resource Center to End Domestic Violence training manual, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Referral book, 2001, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - AIDS awareness, 1999 (Box 5)
    - AIDS information (Box 6)
    - How to Write a Business Plan (Box 6)
    - Well Women health care (Box 6)
    - Women's Health in Women's Hands, (Folders 1-8 of 9) (Box 6)
    - Women's Health in Women's Hands, (Folder 9 of 9) (Box 7)
    - FWHC Executive Summary, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Protocols- old (Box 7)
    - Medical Director agreement- original (Box 7)
    - Medical Practice Act, 1974 (Box 7)
    - FDC and regulations (Box 7)
    - Clinic inspection to-do list (Box 7)
    - Disaster plan, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Disaster preparedness plan approval letter, 1985 May 23 (Box 7)
    - Independent contractor's agreement regarding informed consent (Box 7)
    - Business license- Athens, 1984-1990 (Box 7)
    - Medical professional employment application (Box 7)
    - Protocols- original (Box 7)
    - Planned Parenthood (Box 7)
    - Nurse duties (Box 7)
    - NAF standards, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Hazardous waste transmittal forms (Box 7)
    - Instrument sterilization logs, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
    - Protocols- services, 1989 May 30 (Box 7)
    - Quality assurance mechanisms (Box 7)
    - Registration manuals and Georgia code, 1983 Jan (Box 7)
    - Regulation application, 1980 May (Box 7)
    - Regulations (Box 7)
    - Clinic regulations (Box 7)
    - Expenses, 1989 Feb (Box 7)
    - Maps (Box 7)
    - Weekly instrument checklist, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Instrument log, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Vancouver Women's Health Collective (Box 7)
    - Resolve of Georgia, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Training (Box 8)
    - Test procedures, 1994-1999 (Box 8)
    - All scripts orders, 2002 Feb (Box 8)
    - Henry Schein orders, 2002 (Box 8)
    - H.D. Smith orders, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Integrated Regional Laboratories, 2001 Oct (Box 8)
    - NAF orders, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Office Depot orders, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Articles (Box 8)
    - Clinical procedures and tests (Box 8)
    - On call information/training, 2000 (Box 8)
    - On-call collom (Box 8)
    - Job description, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Job descriptions- archives (Box 8)
    - Testing personnel (Box 8)
    - Laboratory training and employee testing, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Laminaria insertion guidelines (Box 8)
    - Vital signs (Box 8)
    - Health worker step 2 training test answer sheet (Box 8)
    - Vital sign (TPR/OP) test and answer key (Box 8)
    - First trimester explanation/authorization and consent (Box 8)
    - Sterile room/tissue evaluation (Box 8)
    - Hematocrit (Box 8)
    - RH factor (Box 8)
    - Urine dip stick (Box 8)
    - Pregnancy screening/sonogram training (Box 8)
    - Emergency contraceptive training, 1997 (Box 8)
    - General referrals (Box 8)
    - Computer records, 1996-1999 Jul, (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 8)
    - Computer records, 1996-1999 Jul, (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 9)
    - Computer records, 1999 Aug-2000 Jan, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Computer information, 2000 (Box 9)
    - Y2K computer records (Box 9)
    - Computer information, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
    - FWHC employee handbook, 1992 Jan 1 (Box 9)
    - FWHC medical staff bylaws, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Specific duties of nurse in abortion clinic (Box 9)
    - Orientation/training manual for clinic employees, 1984 Apr (Box 10)
    - Medical procedures and protocols (Box 10)
    - Infection control manual (Box 10)
    - Clinic administration, 1980s (Box 10)
    - Clinic guidelines/standardized procedures, 1984 Apr (Box 10)
    - Nurse practitioner protocols (Box 10)
    - Disaster drill, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
    - Disaster preparedness plan, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Disaster preparedness plan, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) training, 1988 (Box 10)
    - The OSHA Safety Plan Book, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Exposure control plan and record forms, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Evacuation drill forms, 1998-1999 (Box 11)
    - BFI (Med-X manifests, bio hazard waste), 1997-1999 (Box 11)
    - Lea's Shield questionnaire (Box 11)
    - Grant report: First Time, First Choice, 1996 (Box 11)
    - FWHC training documents (Box 11)
    - Lab protocols, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
    - Job descriptions (Box 11)
    - American Medical Association (AMA) basic life support (Box 11)
    - Well Woman protocols, 1994 (Box 11)
    - Well Woman protocols, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Manual vacuum aspiration: clinical programmatic experience (Box 12)
    - Trainers' manual (Box 12)
    - Guidelines for use of Methotrexate and Misoprostol (Box 12)
    - Abortion services handbook (Box 12)
    - NAF clinical policy guidelines, 1996-2002, (5 Folders) (Box 12)
    - Administrative policies and procedures for clinics, 1992 (Box 12)
    - Administrative policies and procedures for clinical managers, 1993 (Box 12)
    - Abortion forms (Box 12)
    - Security trust (Box 12)
    - Medical peer review samples (Box 12)
    - Parental notification (Box 12)
    - Department of Human Resources (DHR) questionnaire, 1987 (Box 12)
    - DHR packet, 2002 Aug 20 (Box 12)
    - DHR questionnaire, 1988 (Box 12)
    - DHR questionnaire, 1989 (Box 12)
    - DHR questionnaire, 1990 (Box 12)
    - DHR regulations (Box 12)
    - NARAL literature (Box 12)
    - Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice, 2002 Jun (Box 12)
    - DHR Packet, 2002 Aug 20, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - AIDS Hotline for Women (AHW), 1993 (Box 13)
    - Trademark Reservation, Women's Choice Clinic (Box 13)
    - FWHC newsletters (Box 13)
    - Consent Order: Black v. Atlanta (Box 13)
    - Over-forty services (Box 13)
    - Administrative forms (Box 13)
    - Old to-do lists, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
    - Billing in-service, 2002 Oct 25 (Box 13)
    - Employee handbook, 1992 Jan (Box 13)
    - Disaster drills, 1995-1997 (Box 13)
    - NAF supplemental insurance, 2002 (Box 13)